Guide to the Harriet Oxman Papers 1907-2017 (bulk, 1962-1987) MS 2922
New-York Historical Society
Harriet Oxman papers
1907-2017 (bulk, 1962-1987)
New-York Historical Society
Oxman, Harriet, 1927-2019
MS 2922
1.42 Linear feet (in 2 boxes)
Diaries, correspondence, clippings, publications, and ephemera relating to the career of New York City educator Harriet Oxman, fifth and only female principal of Erasmus Hall High School in Brooklyn (1972-1982). Includes Oxman's self-published The Rise and Fall, Erasmus Hall High School (2017).
Arrangement
The collection is organized in four series:
Series I. Principal's diaries, 1972-1980
Series II. Correspondence, 1965-2017
Series III. Print matter and ephemera, 1949-2017
Series IV. Postcards and photographs, 1907-1912, 1975-1987
Material is sorted chronologically within each series.
Biographical/Historical Note
Harriet Morel Oxman (1927-2019) was a career educator who served the New York City school system from 1954 to 1982. A graduate of Cornell University's School of Industrial and Labor Relations and New York University's School of Education, Oxman was hired in 1957 to teach social studies at Erasmus Hall High School in Brooklyn, where she would rise to grade advisor, guidance counselor, assistant principal in 1964, and principal in 1972, a position she held for a decade. Oxman was the fifth and only female principal in the long history of Erasmus.
Erasmus Hall High School (899-925 Flatbush Avenue, Brooklyn, New York), descends from Erasmus Hall Academy, a private institution named for Dutch scholar and theologian Desiderius Erasmus (1466–1536). Erasmus Hall was founded in 1786 to educate the sons of the Dutch-speaking settlers of Flatbush, then an independent town of Kings County. It was the first secondary school to be chartered by the New York Board of Regents. The Academy building, constructed in 1787 in the Georgian and Federal styles, still stands and is an official New York City landmark. Flatbush was annexed by the City of Brooklyn in 1894, and Erasmus Hall was absorbed by the Brooklyn Board of Education. When Brooklyn joined Greater New York City in 1898, control of Erasmus Hall next went to the New York City Board of Education, which, between 1905 and 1940, constructed the current Collegiate Gothic buildings around the 1787 structure.
Harriet Oxman's tenure as principal (1972–1982) coincided with a period of decline in New York City's schools. Erasmus Hall, in the heart of then crime-ridden Flatbush, saw frequent violence and generally poor academic performance. In 1994, Erasmus was split internally in three separate schools: Humanities, Science and Mathematics, and Business and Technology. 2004 and 2006 saw the additions of the High School for Service and Learning and the Academy for Hospitality and Tourism.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection combines three accessions donated to the New-York Historical Society by Harriet Oxman in 2012 (MS.2012.02), 2017 (MS.2017.31), and 2019 (MS.2019.030).
Related Archival Materials
The New-York Historical Society holds the records of Erasmus Hall High School, 1775-1975, which include material relating to Brooklyn (particularly Flatbush) and prominent area families such as Cowenhoven, Lefferts, Lott, Vanderveer, and Zabriskie, and contain correspondence, minute books, papers, account and record books, maps, publications, photographs, printed material, and memorabilia. A printed index to the collection is available on-site.
Scope and Contents
At the heart of Harriet Oxman's papers are the nine notebooks she kept as principal of Erasmus Hall High School between 1972 and 1980, in which she recorded daily happenings—not all of them pleasant—of the school and its community. Correspondence from alumni (1986–2005) recalls happier experiences. These are reflected by the various publications in the collection: school guides, commencement programs, clippings from The Dutchman, the school's official newspaper, and Oxman's own The Rise and Fall, Erasmus Hall High School, Brooklyn, New York (self-published, 2017). Early twentieth-century postcards issued for the school's 125th anniversary, and photographs of its participation in the U.S. Bicentennial (1975-1976) and its own bicentennial celebrations (1987), round out the collection.
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Schools -- New York (State) -- New York.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; High school principals -- New York (State) -- New York.; Photographs.; Postcards.; Programs (documents).; Oxman, Harriet, 1927-2019; Erasmus Hall High School; Erasmus Hall Academy (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I. Principal's diaries, 1972-1980
  Scope and Contents
  Repurposed red notebooks (labeled "Science-Biology") in which Oxman, as principal of Erasmus Hall, recorded staff names, addresses, telephone numbers; school activities and difficulties (e.g., bomb scares); calls from parents; community events; conversations; student demonstrations (e.g., anti-war), etc.
  - Principal's diary, 1972 February – 1972 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Principal's diary, 1972 September – 1973 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Principal's diary, 1973 September – 1974 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Principal's diary, 1974 September – 1975 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Principal's diary, 1975 September – 1976 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Principal's diary, 1976 September – 1977 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Principal's diary, 1977 September – 1978 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Principal's diary, 1978 September – 1979 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Principal's diary, 1979 September – 1980 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - [notebook], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    A spiral-bound notebook with three pages of manuscript notes by Oxman. Undated, but Staples brand notebook is copyrighted 2011.
- Series II. Correspondence, 1965-2017
  A letter from Oxman in 1976 to the principal of Erasmus Hall in 2076, with correspondence from alumni, and a 1981 thank-you note from President Ronald Reagan.
  - Miscellaneous letters, 1965, 1974-2017 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes a printed note on White House stationery, signed by President Ronald Regan, thanking Harriet Oxman for her "get-well message." Postmarked 5 May 1981, just over a month after John Hinckley Jr.'s failed attempt to assassinate the president.
  - "To the Principal of Erasmus Hall High School in 2076", 1976 December (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    Mulitple copies of a letter written by Harriet Oxman, principal of Erasmus Hall in 1976, to the person holding her position a century in the future. A copy was placed in a time capsule on the campus grounds. The letter is reproduced in Oxman's The Rise and Fall, Erasmus Hall High School (2017), pp. 61-66 (box 2, folders 27-29).
  - Letters from Erasmus Hall alumni, 1986-2005 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    Oxman apparently solicited alumni memories for inclusion in her 2017 work The Rise and Fall, Erasmus Hall High School (see folders 25-26).
- Series III. Print matter and ephemera, 1949-2017
  Published material relating to Erasmus Hall High School, its Parent-Teacher Association, and its Alumni Association, as well as clippings from The Dutchman, the Erasmus newspaper.
  - Harriet Morel [Oxman]. "An Autobiography of a College Student", 1949 May 11 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - Harriet Oxman. "Autobiographical Study of Harriet Oxman", circa 1957 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Erasmus Hall Guide, 1959, 1974 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
    Four copies of 1974, plus two photocopies of the same.
  - Erasmus Hall miscellanea, 1960-1978, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - Erasmus Hall yearbook extracts, 1960-1981 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Erasmus Hall commencement programs, 1960, 1975, 1981, 1984 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    1984 includes typescript of Principal Oxman's speech
  - Dutchman clippings, 1962-1974, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
  - Erasmus Hall P.T.A., 1962-1974 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
  - Erasmus Hall clippings, 1962-2004 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
  - Testimonial programs, 1964-1974 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
    1964 | Testimonial Luncheon, Miss Grace Corey (May 9)
    1965 | Testimonial Luncheon, John F. McNeill, Principal, Erasmus Hall H.S. (May 22)
    1974 | Flatbush Business and Professional Women's Club, honoring Grace Flippinger and Harriet Oxman (March 7)
  - Roland H. Bainton. Erasmus of Christendom (New York: Charles Scribner's Sons), 1969 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
    Book discarded from the Briarcliff High School Library, Briarcliff Manor, New York.
  - Erasmian, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
  - Harriet Oxman clippings, 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
  - Board of Education of the City of New York. Directory of the Public High Schools, 1980-1981 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
  - Harriet Oxman reminiscences, 1980, 1989 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
    Contains "Education and Discipline in the Schools" [subtitled "A day in the life of a Principal"] (1980), "The Case of the Dean and the Voodoo doll" (1980), "I'd like to get a refund or return the article" (1980), and "Erasmus Hall High School--Special Memories" (1989).
  - Erasmus Hall Bicentennial, 1987 September 26-27 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
  - The Chronicles of Erasmus Hall High School, 1937–1987 (New York City Board of Education) [sampler] (2 copies) (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  - The Chronicles of Erasmus Hall High School, 1937–1987 (New York City Board of Education) [full version] (2 copies) (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21-22)
  - Erasmus Hall Museum of Education Guide, 1987 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
  - Erasmus Hall Alumni Association directories, 1996, 2003 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
  - Erasmus Hall Fourth Century Reunion, 2001 March 3 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
    Program and souvenir photo of Oxman.
  - Sue Roberts. "A Tribute to Harriet, A Fiery Opal", 2012 May 17 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
  - Harriet Morel Oxman. The Rise and Fall, Erasmus Hall High School, Brooklyn, New York [3 copies], 2017 August 9 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27-29)
- Series IV. Postcards and photographs, 1907-1912, 1975-1987
  Postcards depicting Erasmus Hall and vicinity, with some photographs of the school's participation in the U.S. Bicentennial (1975-1976) and its own bicentennial celebrations (1787).
  - postcards | Erasmus Hall [21 cards], 1907-1908, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 30)
  - postcards | Official Souvenirs for the One Hundred and Twenty-fifth Anniversary of Erasmus Hall, October 10 and 11, 1912 [12 cards] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 31)
  - postcards | The Erasmus Pageant [11 cards], 1912 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 32)
  - postcards | Historic Flatbush [12 cards], [1975] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 33)
    From an envelope stamped "A Complimentary Souvenir of the Second Annual Dinner of TOFCCA. The Montauk Club, June 7, 1975."
  - photographs | Erasmus Hall [16 photos], 1975-1976, 1979, 1987 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 34)
    Images of [U.S.] Bicentennial Fair, May 1975 and June 1976; Commencement, June 1979; Erasmus Hall Bicentennial, 1987.